Guide to the Dorothy E. Roberts Papers, 1903-1993
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Dorothy E. Roberts papers 1903-1993
University Archives, Duke University
Roberts, Dorothy Elaine.
2.5 Linear Feet approx. 2000 Items
Dorothy Roberts worked in the Dept. of English's administration office from 1948 until her retirement in the late 1980's-early 1990's.
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, printed material and other items created and collected by Dorothy Roberts about the Dept. of English at Duke University. Files largely pertain to the history of the department, focusing heavily on departmental faculty. The collection ranges in date from 1903-1993.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Dorothy E. Roberts Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1982, 2011.
Biographical Note
Dorothy "Dot" Roberts was born in Crewe, Virginia and graduated from the University of Richmond with a major in history and a minor in English. She was hired by Duke University in 1948 to work as the office manager for the Dept. of English and was made administrative assistant in 1967. During her time with the department, Roberts worked for 12 different chairmen. She also established many long-lasting friendships with students and faculty during her time at Duke, including Reynolds Price for whom she typed many of his books, her favorite being "A Long and Happy Life." She retired from Duke in the late 1980's/early 1990's and passed away on Feb. 10, 2002.
Collection Overview
The collection largely consists of material compiled by Roberts, who functioned as historian of the Dept. of English. Of note are the various lists of faculty, Ph.D. candidates and staff of the department over a number of years. Also included are files she maintained on faculty members, which include correspondence and clippings as well as a file Roberts kept on herself regarding her career at Duke. She also provides her impressions of key departmental staff, namely the chairmen she worked for. In 1982, Roberts donated 14 letters between her and Guy Davenport, a Duke alumnus, regarding Paris and other European cities as well of Davenport's appreciation of James Joyce and Roberts' own love of traveling abroad. Roberts' friendship with Reynolds Price is represented in the collection. There are several folders on him which include correspondence, Christmas cards, photographs, clippings, and an envelope which holds locks of Price's hair. Of particular note is a sketch Price drew of Emily Dickinson that he gave to Roberts. There is also a caricature of Ph.D. candidates, including Price, from 1962.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Roberts, Dorothy Elaine
Price, Reynolds, 1933-2011
Davenport, Guy
Duke University. Dept. of English
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University -- Employees
Duke University -- Students -- Caricatures and cartoons
Joyce, James, 1882-1941
Authors, American-20th century -- Correspondence
Europe -- Description and travel
Related Material
Dept. of English Records
Duke University Archives
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (3 boxes)
  - Aiken, Ralph, 1958-1959, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Applewhite, James, 1977, 1983
  - Armstrong, Joseph, 1903-1986
  - Baum, Paull F., 1980-1986, undated
  - Bevington, Helen, 1983 (includes black and white photo of 1965 Campus Club meeting with Reynolds Price)
  - Blackburn, Roma, 1972, 1983
  - Blackburn, William, 1973-1977, 1983-1985
  - Boyce, Ben, 1962-1970, undated
  - Brown, Frank C., 1977-1981
  - Budd, Louis, 1982-1984
  - Chappell, Fred, 1985
  - Clubbe, John, mid-1960s-1978, undated
  - Cunningham, John, undated
  - Davenport, Guy, 1949
  - Davenport, Guy, 1966, 1981-1986
  - Dearlove, Judy, 1981
  - Durden, Bob, 1944, undated
  - Ferguson, Joanne, 1982-1983
  - Ferguson, Oliver, 1959-1975
  - Fish, Stanley, 1985-1986
  - Fish, Stanley, 1987-1992 (2 folders)
  - Gilbert, Allan, 1981-1982, 1987
  - Gohdes, Clarence, 1960's-1980's
  - Gohdes, Clarence, Pioneers in English at Trinity and Duke, 1987-1988
  - Gopen, George, 1986
  - Gurganus, Allan, 1978, 1989
  - Hubbell, Jay B., 1970-1977, 1984
  - Irving, W. H., 1953, 1979
  - Jackson, David K., 1982
  - Jordan, A. C., 1984
  - Kaufman, Wally, 1961-1993
  - Krueger, Robert, 1960's-1980's
  - Lentricchia, Frank, 1966, 1984, 1988
  - Mitchell, Frank, 1967
  - Morgan, Mary, 1985-1986
  - Patton, Lewis, 1972-1989
  - Reardon, Kenneth, 1971, 1980
  - Reiss, Ed, 1978, 1983, 1985
  - Ryals, Clyde, 1981 Sept. 4
  - Spivey, Robert, 1978, 1984, undated
  - Stevenson, Lionel, 1970-1972, undated
  - Styron, William, 1980, 1984
  - Truesdale, J. (song), undated
  - Tompkins, Jane, 1986, 1993
  - Torgovnick, Marianna, 1983
  - Turner, Arlin, 1962, 1981
  - Tyler, Anne, 1986, 1991
  - Voll, Daniel, 1986
  - Ward, Charles E., 1967-1968
  - White, Newman I., 1947-1948, 1979, undated
  - Williams, Kenny J., 1982-1992
  - Professorships, 1982
  - English 103-104, 1960's-1980's
  - English 106, 1974-1986
  - Freshman English
  - Major Requirements (history of)
  - Accounts of Chairmen - English Dept., 1979-1984
  - Full-time Staff, 1947-1985
  - English Dept. Staff Lists
  - Afro-American Studies - History
  - Duke Press (history of) and American Literature (history of), 1951, 1982-1984
  - THE ARCHIVE (history of)
  - Awards
  - Beginnings: Trinity and Duke
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984
  - Greatest Novels
  - Letters of Commendation, 1950-1976, undated
  - English Dept. Newsletter, 1983-1991/1992
  - Distinguised Professors of Duke University, 1979
  - Inauguration Program: H. Keith H. Brodie, 1985 Sept. 28
  - Ph.D.'s Directed
  - Anne Flexner Award, 1971-1980
  - Freshman English
  - English Dept. Seniority Lists, 1967-1986
  - English Dept. Lists
  - English Dept. Data (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Sketch of Emily Dickinson by Reynolds Price, 1950
  - Caricatures of English Dept. Ph.D. Candidates, including Reynolds Price, by Marie C. Combs, 1962
  - Reynolds Price Bibliography
  - Reynolds Price: Correspondence, Notes from Gifts, 1980's
  - Reynolds Price: List of 10 Greatest Novels, 1970 June
  - Reynolds Price: Christmas Card,s 1969-1978
  - Reynolds Price: Postcards
  - Reynolds Price: Correspondence, 1961-1966
  - Reynolds Price: Correspondence, 1967-1969, 1970's (2 folders)
  - Reynolds Price: Clippings
  - Reynolds Price: Photographs and Hair
  - Dot Roberts, 1947-1983 (Box 3)
  - Notes on English Dept.
  - Duke University Postcards
  - Photograph: Chapel Drive, undated
  - Clippings
  - Printed Material